-我得走了  -当然  去吧
- I'll have to go. - Of course you must go.
谁去把信交给夫人呢
Oh, but who'll give the letter to her ladyship?
我去吧
Oh, I can do that and
今天由我来服侍夫人用餐更衣
I'll take her breakfast and dress her today,
但这不是长久之计
but I haven't got time to make it a regular thing.
找到替任之前  我来服侍夫人
No, I can do it until she finds someone else.
玛丽小姐不会介意的
Lady Mary won't mind.
-你怎么了  -奥布瑞恩小姐突然走了
- What's the matter with you? - Miss O'Brien's upped and left!
不可能
Never!
吉米
Jimmy!
吉米  奥布瑞恩小姐走了
Jimmy. Miss O'Brien's gone!
-什么  去哪了  -我怎么知道
- What? Gone where? - How should I know?
玛姬  奥布瑞恩走了
Madge, O'Brien's gone.
-你听说了吗  -什么
- Have you heard? - Heard what?
-奥布瑞恩小姐走了  -什么叫走了
- Miss O'Brien? She's gone. - What do you mean gone?
-她离开了  -离开
- She's left. - Left?
她打包走人了
She's packed up.
真无法相信
I can't believe it.
我不觉得  像贼一样夜里偷偷出走
I can. Sneaking off like a thief in the night,
真是奥布瑞恩的风格
that's O'Brien to a T.
我是不相信苏珊竟会抢我的人
I just can't believe Susan has done this to me.
奥布瑞恩小姐确实说过
Miss O'Brien did say that
弗林特夏尔夫人与她在苏格兰时
she got on very well with Lady Flintshire
相处甚欢
when she was up in Scotland.
我想也是
So I gather!
弗林特夏尔夫人已为我订了去印度的车票
"Lady Flintshire has booked my ticket for India
机会难得  错过实在可惜
"And it seems too good a chance to miss."
真的毫无预兆
Was there really no warning?
现在想来  昨天她接到一通电报
Now I think of it, she'd a telegram yesterday.
一定是为这事
That must have been it.
现在怎么办
So what happens now?
今天由我为您更衣  夫人
I'll dress you today, m'lady,
明天安娜会接手  直到您找到新的贴身女仆
and Anna will take over tomorrow, until you find a replacement.
她真的完全没表露出来吗
And she really gave no clue?
她对我只字未提  卡森先生
She didn't say anything to me, Mr Carson, not a word.
当真如此吗
As long as she didn't.
我知道你们都以为她有说什么  但确实没有
I know you all think she must have said summat, but she didn't.
我信你  可你难以服众啊
I believe you. Thousands wouldn't.
她是我的姨妈  可她心思一向难测
She may be my aunt but she's a dark horse.
这点倒是无人不服
No-one will contradict you there.
苏珊・弗林特夏尔偷了妈妈的女仆
Susan Flintshire has stolen Mama's maid
她女儿还在我们家作客呢
whilst her daughter's a guest in this house?
她肯定不会这么说
I'm sure she wouldn't put it like that.
我管她怎么说  这太下作了
I don't care how she puts it. It's absolutely disgraceful.
-没事  玛姬和我说了  -当然有事
- It's all right. Madge told me. - It is NOT all right.
-你真毫不知情吗  -不知道
- Did you have any idea? - No. Not really.
我知道  妈妈觉得
I knew, I knew that Mummy
奥布瑞恩很会做头发
thought O'Brien was very good at doing hair,
他们还说过  奥布瑞恩想去旅行
and they talked about her wanting to travel...
-什么时候  -你们在唐伊阁的时候
- What? When? - When you were all at Duneagle.
你竟然没告诉我们
And you didn't think to inform us?
我明天去伦敦  可以在《女士》杂志上登则广告
I'm in London tomorrow. I can put an advertisement in The Lady.
很好
Good.
等杂志刊登信息会不会要很久
Won't it take forever, waiting for the magazine to come out?
这也没办法
It can't be helped.
我们十一点要见特伦特
We're meeting Trent at eleven.
到时见  我想先去种植园走走
I'll see you there. I want to walk the plantations first.
不知道玛丽想不想一起去
I was wondering if Mary might like to come.
别打扰玛丽  她够烦的了
Don't bother Mary. She's got enough on her plate.
你真的什么都不知道
Did you really not know anything?
我没想到她真会这么做
I never thought she'd go through with it.
我想您该带上这件
I thought you might like to take this down with you.
要是您想出去走走  外头挺冷的
In case you want a walk. It's quite chilly.
黑色那件呢
Where's the black one?
我带乔治少爷去散散步  小姐
I'm taking Master George out for some air, m'lady,
您要一起来吗
and I wondered if you'd like to come with us.
不了  谢谢
I don't think so, but thank you.
可怜的小孤儿
Poor little orphan.
谢谢  保姆
Thank you, Nanny.
他不是孤儿  他有母亲
He's not an orphan. He's got his mother.
孤儿没有
Orphans haven't.
要这么说  他也不可怜[穷]
He isn't poor either, come to that.
您不介意我照顾夫人吧
And you don't mind my seeing to her ladyship?
为何介意  我又没打算环游世界
Why would I mind? I'm not planning a trip round the world.
莫斯利先生  你看见崔维斯先生了吗
Mr Molesley. Have you seen Mr Travis?
我要和他谈慈善集市的事
I need to speak to him about the Bring and Buy Sale.
没见着  夫人
I'm afraid not, your ladyship.
好吧
Never mind.
真是令人伤感啊
This were a sad business.
悲伤之极
Very, very sad.
真不敢相信  已经到立碑的时候了
I can't believe it's time for the stone already.
六个月了
Six months.
安顿坟墓需要六个月
They always leave six months for the grave to settle.
你儿子找到新工作了吗
Tell me has, has your son found another job, yet?
没  夫人
No, m'lady.
他们留下他了
They've let him stay on
他也总是很努力
and he always tries to make himself useful,
但也不能长久如此
but it can't go on forever
而且  他还没了薪水
and anyway, he's lost his wage.
但他是个训练有素的贴身男仆
But he's a properly trained valet.
还可以当个管家
He could even be a butler.
我倒希望如此  夫人
I hope so, m'lady...
但世道多变啊
..But it's a changing world.
这点我清楚得很
You don't have to tell me.
你好啊
Hello.
你很快就能走路了  小姐
It'll soon be time for you to get out and walk, young lady.
请不要在未经我允许的情况下碰这孩子
Please don't touch the children, not without my permission.
什么
What?
照看他们是我的责任  再小心也不为过
They are in my charge and I cannot be too careful.
你可别忘了  我认识这孩子的母亲
I would remind you that I knew this young girl's mother,
跟你不一样
which you never did.
那并不代表你是她的朋友
That doesn't make you her friend.
我确实是她的朋友
As a matter of fact, it does.
我没时间跟你拌嘴
Well, I can't stay here to bandy words.
你能不能转告帕特莫太太
Will you ask Mrs Patmore
让她在半小时内备好孩子的午餐
to send up the children's luncheon in half an hour?
你自己跟她说吧
Ask her yourself, why don't you?
夫人是不是很失望
Was her ladyship very disappointed?
是  而且得一阵子才能找到合适的人选
She was, and it'll take quite a while to find a replacement.
真没想到奥布瑞恩小姐这么欠考虑
I can't believe Miss O'Brien would be so thoughtless.
出乎意料吗  我倒不觉得
Can't you? I can.
她想出去冒险  这有什么不妥的
She wants an adventure. What's wrong with that?
反正我不怪她
I don't blame her.
她可以离开
Not for wanting to go,
但别突然就跑了  让大家措手不及
but why run off and leave us in the lurch?
你这么说是想让大家觉得你事先也不知情吧
You're talking like that so we'll think you didn't know.
怎么能这么说呢
That's not kind!
拉着个脸有什么用  祝她好运
What's the good of a month of sour looks? Good luck to her.
-玛丽小姐今早怎么样  -还是老样子
- How was Lady Mary this morning? - The same.
她最终会走出来吧
But, I suppose she must come out of it eventually.
起码也要为乔治少爷考虑一下
For Master George's sake, if for no other reason.
但愿如此
I hope so.
她现在把一切都交给维斯特保姆了
Right now, she prefers to leave it all to Nanny West.
保姆的工作我可做不来
I couldn't be a nanny.
为什么  你不喜欢孩子吗
Why not? Don't you like children?
喜欢是喜欢
No, I do.
但做了保姆的话
Being a nanny
既不算家里人  又不算仆人
you're not one of the family but not one of us either.
-你们在聊什么呢  -做保姆
- What are you talking about? - Being a nanny.
黛西说那种生活一定很孤独
Daisy was saying she thinks it must be a lonely life.
这我倒不知道
I don't know about that.
不过要我说  那个维斯特保姆实在是自恃过高了
But if you ask me, that Nanny West thinks too much of herself.
她怎么了  她一向对我挺好的
Why? What's she done? She always seems nice to me.
她就会对我颐指气使
She only tried to give me orders.
你是说她把你当成仆人了
You mean she mistook you for a servant?
-但他就是个仆人  -这话可别跟他说
- But he IS a servant. - Don't tell him that.
他可承受不了这个打击
He'll never get over the shock!
多谢了  马什先生
Thank you, Mr Marsh.
他失望也在所难免
He was bound to be disappointed.
你真的要放弃整个计划吗
You're really sure you want to abandon the whole plan?
我们别无选择
We don't have a choice.
有一半的地产都要缴继承税
We have to find the death duties on half the estate.
-后果一定不堪设想  -我知道
- And they'll be merciless. - I know.
不过我希望我们能等玛丽回来参与处理这事
But, I wish we could wait for Mary to come back into play.
这本来就不关她的事
She isn't a player.
她生前可以享有马修在唐顿
She has a life interest in one third of Matthew's share of Downton,
和其他地方财产的三分之一
and a third of his other possessions,
但其他的财产都归乔治所有
but everything else belongs to little George.
法律规定她只能继承这么一点吗
And that's all the law gives her?
他该起草一份遗嘱的
He should have made a will.
但玛丽是乔治的监护人
But, Mary's George's guardian.
这难道不能给她点话语权吗
Surely that gives her some sort of say?
说不准
It's a moot point.
既然所有财产的一半都归我所有
Since I own the other half of everything,
由我来管理孩子的财产不是更合适吗
isn't it more appropriate for me to manage the boy's fortunes?
更何况她现在这么脆弱
Besides, she's in such a fragile state,
我真不想让她为财产的事烦心
the last thing I want is for her to start worrying about money.
话虽这么说  但您不觉得...
Of course. But you don't think...?
你知道她是什么样子
You've seen her!
她连吃饭的力气都没有
She hardly has the energy to lift a fork to her mouth.
她很爱他
She loved him very much.
真爱的代价就是其中一方之死所带来的巨大痛苦
And the price of great love is great misery when one of you dies.
-我知道  -是的
- I know that. - Of course you do.
真抱歉
I'm so sorry.
咱们快点回去吧  别耽误了吃午饭
We better get back or we'll be late for lunch.
您知道我登了广告的  卡森先生
I've placed advertisements, Mr Carson, you know I have.
-没有合适的吗  -根本没有回音
- But the answers weren't suitable? - I didn't get any answers.
倒不是完全没有  但我回信之后就没有回音了
Well, I did, but when I wrote back, I heard nothing more.
我不知该说些什么了
Well, I don't know what to suggest.
因为  我不能留在这吗
Because, I can't stay here?
莫斯利先生  我不想显得无理
Mr Molesley, I should hate us to appear inhospitable.
但我不能留在这儿
But I can't stay here.
这对老爷来说公平吗  毕竟都六个月了
Is it fair on his lordship? It has been six months.
我可以去我爸爸那儿  再想办法
I suppose I could go to my dad's until I get something sorted.
好主意
What a good idea.
-午饭准备好了  -谢谢你  帕特莫太太
- Servants' lunch is on the table. - Thank you, Mrs Patmore.
高兴点  莫斯利先生  事情还没定下来呢
Oh cheer up, Mr Molesley. It may never happen.
已经成定局了
It already has.
我午餐后要去瑟斯克  你要一起去吗
By the way, I'm going into Thirsk after lunch. Do you want to come?
我要去村里  看看伊泽贝尔怎么样了
I'm walking down to the village to see how Isobel's getting on.
跟她说  随时可以来
Remind her it's an open invitation,
她要是想看看孙子
if she wants to see her grandson
或是想找人陪陪她  只要过来就行
or feels like company, she just has to turn up.
我会转告她的
I'll tell her.
-我可能会和你一起去  -还是别了
- I might come with you. - I don't think so.
我觉得她可能不想见到太多人
I don't think she's up to seeing many people.
我只是想去村里而已
I only meant into the village.
伊迪丝 你明天真的要去伦敦吗
Edith, are you really going to London tomorrow?
如果你去  我正好有事让你帮我办
I have a couple of errands if you are.
我要去见迈克尔・格莱格森
I'm seeing Michael Gregson.
你留在这里的日子  他一定想死你了
He must have missed you while you've been here.
他要举办一个宴会  把我介绍给他文学圈的朋友
He's giving a party to introduce me to his literary friends.
真令人期待  是不是  罗伯特
How exciting. Isn't it, Robert?
我可不可以放一张卡片在你的橱窗里
I... I was wondering if I might put a card in your window.
-什么样的卡片  小姐  -工作招人的卡片
- A card, m'lady? - For a job asking for applicants.
是什么样的工作呢
And what sort of job might this be?
怎么  这还有什么区别吗
Why? Does it make a difference?
-不  并没有  -谢谢你了
- No, I suppose not. - Thank you.
-我该付你多少钱呢  -六便士就好
- Erm, how much will that be? - Sixpence should cover it.
你真应该多去看看乔治
You ought to see more of George.
可怜的乔治
Poor George.
一出生就命途多舛
What a burden he is born into.
身家阔绰  妈妈却形如枯槁
A baby rich as Croesus and a mother almost passed over.
法律就是如此
That's the law.
感觉好奇怪
It seems so strange.
马修一向谨小慎微
Matthew was always so meticulous.
他以为死亡离他还早得很
He thought that death was many years away.
本来也应该如此
And so it should have been.
如果有什么我能帮忙的  请尽管开口
If there's anything I can do to help, please let me do it.
我很感激
I'm grateful.
但是你看  如果你的独子过世了
But you see, when your only child dies...
你就不再是一个母亲了
..Then you're not a mother any more.
你就什么也不是了
You're not anything, really.
我在努力适应这一点
That's what I'm trying to get used to.
你也是一位祖母
You're a grandmother.
我知道你一定会是位出色的祖母
And I know you're going to be a wonderful one.
-下午送来的信  -谢谢
- Afternoon post. - Ah, thank you.
怎么又这样
Oh, not this again.
怎么了
Not what?
没什么
Oh...nothing!
家具商来了就通知我一声
Let me know when the upholsterer arrives.
你布置工作的时候  我也要在场
I want to be there when you explain the job in hand.
好呀  不过我一人就能办好了
Very well, but I can easily manage.
得让他知道挂毯有多贵重
He needs to grasp the quality of the tapestry on the chairs,
免得他冒冒失失地往上钉钉子
before he starts slamming nails into them.
难道我就交代不明白吗
And I couldn't make him see that?
招工  贴身女仆  会女红和梳头
我们关门了  亲爱的
Just closing, love.
我只想知道是谁在找贴身女仆
I only wanted to know who was looking for a lady's maid.
在唐顿  也只有那几个需要找贴身女仆的
There's not too many in Downton who need a lady's maid.
你是指庄园的人吗
You mean the Abbey?
你以前不是在那里干过吗
Didn't you used to work there?
我干过  但我后来去学东西了
I did, but I've been studying since then.
-学什么  -学习如何做贴身女仆
- Studying for what? - To become a lady's maid.
玛姬说伊迪丝小姐下午去看望了卡劳利夫人
Madge says that Lady Edith saw Mrs Crawley this afternoon.
-她还好吗  -恐怕是非常不好
- How is she? - In a very dark place, I'm afraid.
这也难怪
And no wonder.
一个寡妇  又失去了独子
For a widowed mother to lose an only son...
没有比您更合适去安慰她的人了
There's no more fit person to comfort her than you.
是吗
I wonder.
如果茜玻小姐是我的独女  我怕是活不下去了
If Lady Sybil had been an only child I believe I'd have died.
不  夫人  您会为孩子好好活下去
No, m'lady. You would have lived on for the baby.
她也一样
And so must she.
谢谢你  休斯太太  晚安了
Thank you so much, Mrs Hughes, and good night to you.
晚安  夫人
Good night, m'lady.
老爷
M'lord.
你还好吧
Are you all right?
我觉得我们得定下来
I feel we must settle the question
由谁来打理孩子的财产
of who is to manage the baby's property.
我不想催促玛丽
I don't want to hurry Mary before she's ready.
这有什么可争论的
What question?
她是乔治的妈妈和监护人啊
She's George's mother and his guardian.
当然了
Of course she is,
但是涉及到关于庄园的决定
but when it comes to decisions about the estate,
我来不是更妥当吗
shouldn't it be me?
为什么
Why?
因为我和我的外孙共同拥有六分之五的唐顿
Because, together, my grandson and I own five sixths of Downton.
而玛丽的部分只是有生之年享有
Mary's share is only for her life.
即使她想  也做不了什么
She couldn't do much with it even if she wanted to.
重要的是  因为遗传税的缘故
The point being that with the death duties we're facing,
我们要做出一些重要的决定
there are some big decisions ahead.
你要把玛丽挤出去吗
You want to push Mary out.
我不是要挤她  她本来也没有决定权
I'm not pushing her out. She was never "In."
马修是共同所有人  如今他儿子是
Matthew was co-owner and now his son is.
我曾跟马修共同努力  如今我要为他的儿子努力
I worked with Matthew. I must work for his boy.
谢谢
Thanks.
周二居然有这么多信
A lot of letters for a Tuesday.
这一周刚刚开始  大家哪来的时间写信啊
How do people have time to write when the week is just beginning?
今天是情人节
It's Saint Valentine's Day.
你居然记得这日子  而我却忘了
Oh, imagine your remembering that and my forgetting it.
这谁能想得到啊
Who would have thought such a thing?
我也不是完全不懂浪漫
I am not a complete stranger to romance
如果你是这个意思的话
if that's what you're implying.
或许现在是吧  但也不一直是如此
Maybe I am now, but I wasn't always.
等等  我以为这都是账单呢
Hold on. I thought these were all bills.
黛茜  这封是给你的
Daisy! This one's for you.
黛茜  是谁寄的啊
Daisy? Who's that from?
别取笑她  巴罗先生
Don't tease her, Mr Barrow.
谁给你寄了卡片
Who sent you a card?
我也不知道  上面没有签名
I don't know. It's not signed.
我的也是  看来我们俩都有暗恋者
Nor's mine. We both must have secret admirers.
这也不奇怪嘛
Which is no more than we deserve.
差不多行了  贝茨先生  还有活儿要干呢
That's enough of that, Mr. Bates. We've work to do.
看什么呢
What's that?
没什么
Nothing.
是啊  今天是情人节
Of course. It's Valentine's Day.
你什么时候去伦敦
When are you leaving for London?
十点钟的火车
I'm catching the ten o'clock.
我该去收拾了
I ought to pack.
玩得开心
Have a happy time.
里彭  中央济贫院
上帝是仁慈的
就是那个
Just down there.
格里格先生
Mr. Grigg?
我们认识吗
Do I know you?
你写信给唐顿庄园的查理・卡森
You wrote to Charlie Carson at Downton Abbey.
我们一起工作
I work with him.
是他派你来的吗
Did he send you?
也不尽然
Not exactly. In a way.
他都说我什么了
What... What did he say about me?
他打算怎么办
What does he plan to do?
卡森先生是个大忙人
Mr. Carson is very busy.
他想让我来看看你现在情况如何
He wanted me to find out how you are.
然后  他才能有所打算
Then, I think he'll come up with a plan.
我就知道
I knew it.
上一次见面  他说了许多伤人的话
He said some harsh things when we last met,
但查理和我  我们交情很深
but, we go back a long way, Charlie and me.
所以无论发生什么
And whatever's happened,
当年在戏班子结下的交情  终归还在的
to theatre folk like us, that means something.
是啊  我也这么想
Yes, I'm sure it does.
谢谢  女士  谢谢
Thank you, Madam. Thank you.
这么贴心
This is very lovely.
你这会儿不该在办公室吗
Shouldn't you be at the office?
罗斯孟德姑妈都派车来了
Aunt Rosamund's sending her car.
我很想你
I've missed you.
每时每刻  我都在想你
I haven't stopped thinking about you for one moment.
我不是来了吗
Well, I'm here now.
我听到了一些消息  让我非常激动
I couldn't be more thrilled because I've got some news...
也算不上消息  算是个想法吧
Well, not news, more an idea.
说来听听
Go on.
我研究了一下
I've done some research,
发现并非所有国家都如英格兰一般
and discovered not every country is the same as England.
真是大发现啊
You amaze me.
不  我是说在其他国家
No, I mean there are places
精神失常可以作为离婚的理由
where lunacy is grounds for divorce,
像在葡萄牙  希腊  还有德国
Portugal and Greece and even Germany.
但是  那得是当地居民才行吧
But, wouldn't you have to live there?
不  不  我只是粗浅地了解了一下
No, no, I'm just finding out what's involved.
但如果我真的移民德国  你会和我一起去吗
But if I did live in Germany, would you come with me?
你好  伯恩斯
Oh. Hello, Burns.
这位是伯恩斯  罗斯孟德姑妈的司机
This is Burns, Aunt Rosamund's chauffeur.
下午好  小姐
Good afternoon, m'lady.
需要载你一程吗
Can I give you a lift?
不了  我坐出租就好  方向不同
No, I'll take a taxi. It's the opposite direction.
那晚上见
I'll see you tonight.
是我来得太早了吗
Oh. Am I too early?
不是  是下午茶上晚了
No. I'm afraid tea was a little late.
天呐  你能应付得来吗  要不要我帮忙
Oh, dear. Can you manage? Should I give you a hand?
我能行  谢谢  维斯特小姐
I can manage, thank you, Miss West.
快来  小宝贝
Come to me, darling.
你好啊
Hello.
您的小王子来了  小姐
Now, here's the little Prince, m'lady.
您瞧他看到您有多高兴啊
See how happy he is to see his beautiful Mama?
上帝保佑他
God bless him.
谢谢你  保姆
Thank you, Nanny.
你说你失去了人生的目标
You say you have no purpose,
可小乔治怎么办
but what about little George?
你肯定很关心他的
Surely you're interested in him?
当然  但我不想多插手  让玛丽不悦
Of course, but I'm not going to drive Mary mad by interfering.
做奶奶的就得插手
It's the job of grandmothers to interfere.
是莫斯利来了
Oh, that's Molesley.
他想见我  所以我们约好了时间
He asked to see me and I told him when he could come.
是吗  我能留下吗
Oh? Well, may I stay?
还是你有秘密任务要安排
Or is it a secret assignation?
很抱歉打扰二位夫人了
Oh. I'm very sorry to interrupt your ladyship.
找我什么事  莫斯利
What is it, Molesley?
我想问问您  能否考虑让我重新回来工作
I came to ask if you'd consider giving me my old job back.
不好意思  打扰你们谈私事了
I apologise for forcing myself on a private conversation.
我这就走
I will go.
请别走  夫人  没什么秘密可言
No please, m'lady. There's no mystery.
因为那件事  我丢了工作
I've lost my job, because, well, for obvious reasons
所以我想能不能回来工作
and I thought I'd ask here.
问题是  我并不需要管家
The trouble is, I have no need for a butler.
如今我只是个用托盘吃饭的老寡妇
These days I'm just an old widow who eats off a tray.
我明白
I see.
不能因为自己是个老寡妇
Just because you're an old widow,
就用托盘吃饭啊
I see no necessity to eat off a tray.
我们俩可是不是同一种人
You and I are different.
没错  这话不假
Yes, that is very true.
浪费您的时间了
I'm wasting your time.
要是有空缺的职位
Should, should we hear of an opening...
我们应该上哪找你呢
..where would we find you?
我会搬去我父亲那儿  夫人
I'm moving to my father's house, m'lady.
你有想过我对你说的话吗
Have you had any more time to think about what I said?
你是说我们罪恶地生活在一起
You mean our living in sin?
如果我离婚了  就不算罪恶了
We'd only live in sin as you call it, until the divorce.
你不想跟我在一起吗
Don't you want to be with me?
你知道我想的  求之若渴
You know I do. More than anything.
还有杜松子酒吗  先生  快喝完了
Erm, is there any more gin, sir? We're running rather low.
好的  我...我去看看
Yes, I'll er, I'll have a look.
上帝啊
Oh, my Lord!
不胜荣幸  老夫人
This is an honour, your ladyship.
我给你儿子捎个话
I have a message for your son.
沙克尔顿夫人要来与我共进午宴
Lady Shackleton is joining me for luncheon.
我想让他过来帮忙
I want him to come and help.
那斯普拉特先生呢
But, what about Mr Spratt?
斯普拉特当然也在
Well, Spratt will be there, of course,
但莫斯利还是可以帮忙嘛
but Molesley can still take an active part.
沙克尔顿夫人告诉我说她的管家要退休了
Lady Shackleton tells me her butler is retiring.
那她不是要想办法另寻他人吗
Won't she have made arrangements to find another?
关键就在这里
But that is the point.
她还没有决定是否要找人接替他
She hasn't yet decided whether to replace him or not,
所以要是莫斯利能够一展身手的话...
so if Molesley can demonstrate his skills...
斯普拉特先生不介意吗
Mr Spratt won't mind?
还轮不到他来介意
It is not his business to mind.
那是当然  那么...
No. Well...
好的  夫人  非常感谢
Very good, m'lady. Thank you very much.
我已经把那封信揉成一团扔掉了
You took a letter out of my waste paper basket
你竟然还把它从我的废纸篓里捡了出来
when I had clearly crumpled it and thrown it away?
我知道你不开心了
I could see it had upset you.
我想知道为什么
I wanted to know why.
那是自然
I'm sure.
但你有没有想过
But it didn't occur to you
你或许不该操心我为什么不开心
it might not be your concern WHY I was upset?
不管怎样  我操了心  读了信
Well, anyway, I did it and I read it
我还去见了他
and I went to see him!
你难道不想知道他境况如何吗
Don't you want to know how he is?
我要是想知道的话  我就回信给他了
If I wanted to know how he is, I would have answered his letter.
卡森先生  他在济贫院里
Mr Carson, he's in the workhouse!
如果你想知道
And in case you're wondering,
那里就跟狄更斯的小说里描述的一样糟糕
it's as bad as if we were reading about it in a novel by Dickens.
济贫院不是应该都已经关闭了吗
Haven't they closed the workhouses?
没有  还留下来了一些
No. They haven't. Not all of them.
起码雨淋不着他
Well, at least he's in the dry.
雨倒是淋不着他
If you can call it dry
可是那里的每一寸空气都弥漫着霉味
when there's mould in the very air you breathe.
这个男人曾经跟你一起唱歌跳舞
This is a man you sang and danced with.
你真的无动于衷吗
Do you feel nothing?
我想我帮不上忙
I don't feel I could be helpful, no.
而且那是我想要忘掉的一段时光
And I would thank you not to remind me
我希望你不要再提
of a time in my life I prefer to forget.
可我们为什么需要这个
But why would we need it?
这是个搅拌机  可以打蛋  搅奶油什么的
It's a mixer. It beats eggs and whips cream and all sorts.
可那是你跟艾薇的活儿
But you and Ivy do that!
我们可巴不得不干那活儿呢
And we'd be glad not to, thank you very much.
伊迪丝小姐有没有说为什么买这个
Did Lady Edith say why she got it?
夫人让她买的
Her ladyship asked her to.
她想让我们省点力气
She wants to save us a bit of elbow grease.
你们两个傻丫头
You don't understand!
要不了多久
Before too long,
夫人就可以随便找个村妇来管厨房了
her ladyship could run the kitchen with a woman from the village.
这些面包机啊
What with these toasters and
搅拌机啊什么的  要害我们失业了
mixers and such like, we'd be out of a job.
-我想试试嘛  -那随你的便
- I want to try it. - Then on your own head be it!
你喜欢你的卡片吗  艾薇
Did you like your card, Ivy?
关你什么事
What's it to you?
这还不明显
That'd be telling.
别听他的  他在逗你呢
Don't listen. He's just teasing.
好啦  你们俩走开  该干活了
Come on. Clear out, you two. There's work to be done.
你觉得是不是吉米寄的卡片
Do you think that means that Jimmy sent it?
没准他只是觉得逗我们很好玩吧
Maybe he thinks it fun to tease.
但是  你想过没有
But, don't you see?
如果我的是吉米寄的  那你的是谁寄的
If Jimmy sent mine, then who sent yours?
-托马斯  -你该叫巴罗先生
- Thomas? - Mr Barrow to you.
你能不能跟帕特莫太太说一声
Can you tell Mrs Patmore
茜玻小姐的茶点不要炒蛋
I won't want the scrambled egg for Miss Sybbie's tea.
你从这里走  下楼梯
If you go through here and down the stairs,
就能自己跟她说了
you can tell her yourself.
拜托帮个忙  我忙的不可开交
Do it. Please. I can't stop.
孩子们没人看呢
The children are on their own.
既然罗斯打算去找人
Why did I struggle across
我去伦敦跑腿做什么
London if Rose was going to sort it out?
你还有别的事情要做
You had other things to do.
那也不是罗斯在邮局窗口放广告卡的理由
It doesn't explain why rose put the card in the Post Office window.
我只是觉得如果能找个当地人
I just thought how much quicker
那大概会快得多
it would be if we could find someone local.
我觉得我有责任这么做
I do feel responsible.
你收到任何回复了吗
Have you had any answers yet?
我们收到了三个  其中一个很不错
We've had three and one's promising,
我们会在周五去里彭见她
so we'll see her in Ripon on Friday.
为什么她不来这里
Why isn't she coming here?
她要照顾姨妈  走不开
She's looking after her aunt, she can't get away.
你该回到我们身边来了
It's time for you to come back to us.
你有什么建议
What would you suggest?
找点感兴趣的事情  不管什么事
Take an interest in something, doesn't matter what.
诗歌...或者木艺
Poetry...or carpentry.
-历史或者帽子  -我对乔治感兴趣
- History or hats. - I'm interested in George.
是吗
Are you?
我会的
I will be.
你今天都干了些什么
What have you been doing today?
就是修理车间的各种事情
Well, it's this whole business with the repair shop.
汤姆  别拿那些无聊的事情烦她
Tom, don't bore her with all that nonsense.
-是我的错  我先问他的  -即便如此
- It's my fault. I asked. - Even so.
你要做的就是开心起来
You concentrate on feeling better.
你不必为其他任何事操心
You mustn't worry about anything else.
你寄了情人节贺卡吗
Did you send a Valentine's card?
或许吧
Suppose I did.
-是给艾薇的吗  -这不管你的事
- Was it to Ivy? - That's my business.
你不会真给艾薇寄了卡片吧
You didn't really send Ivy a card?
有可能吗
Is it likely?
我给安斯特拉瑟老夫人寄了一张
I sent one to Lady Anstruther.
我之前在她那儿工作
I used to worked for her
听说她要从法国回来了
and I heard she's coming back from France.
或许能用上她
She might be useful.
你这样会不会太唐突了
Wasn't that a bit forward?
我觉得她不会介意的
Oh, I don't think she'll mind.
说实话  休斯太太
To be honest, Mrs Hughes,
我认为这事与我毫无关系
I don't see that it's any of my business.
真没料到您会说出这种话  夫人
That's something I never thought I'd hear you say, ma'am.
一个在济贫院的可怜人
A wretched man is in the workhouse
他向我们求助
and he reaches out to us for rescue.
他是向卡森求助
Well, he reached out to Carson.
我不知道你想让我做什么
I don't see what you want me to do.
卡劳利夫人  我
Mrs Crawley, I...
我在想能否把他带到这来
I wondered if I could bring him here.
这里
Here?
如果我俩能向当局替他作担保
If you and I were to vouch for him to the authorities,
就一定能把他从那地方弄出来
I'm sure we could get him away from that place.
可为什么带到这儿来  为什么不是唐顿
But why here? Why not the Abbey?
照顾他不该是卡森的责任吗
Isn't he Carson's responsibility?
可遗憾的是
I'm sorry to say it, but,
卡森先生已经对他的老伙计弃之不顾了
Mr Carson has turned his back on his old pal.
我明白了
I see.
所以即使会激怒卡森你也要把他救出来
So you want to risk Carson's wrath by rescuing this Mr Grigg?
他是个可怜的家伙  但还有工作的能力
He's a pitiful being, but he's not beyond work.
如果他有机会还是能过上体面的生活的
He's not beyond a decent life, if he could find it.
可依我现在的情况  恐怕无力...
You see, in my present state, I don't think I'm strong enough...
您可以的  夫人
But you are, ma'am!
只要您能化悲伤为力量
If you could just set aside your grief,
去帮助有需要的人
and use that strength for another's good.
-布兰森先生  -卡森先生
- Mr Branson. - Mr Carson.
我知道你不会认可
I know you won't think it correct,
但我有个难处得求你帮忙
but I need to ask your help in a difficult situation.
求我帮忙  先生
My help, sir?
格兰瑟姆伯爵不同意我这么做
Lord Grantham is against me in this.
马修走了  没人能帮我了
With Matthew gone, I've no-one else to turn to.
玛丽  玛丽小姐的情况丝毫没有好转
Mary, that is, Lady Mary, is not improving.
-她受的打击太大了  -没错
- She's suffered a terrible tragedy. - Of course.
可已经过去六个月了
But it's six months now,
而她没比他刚走一周时好多少
and she's no better than she was a week after he died.
唯一的办法就是转移她的注意力
The only way is for her to find an interest outside of herself,
我认为可以让她来打理庄园
and I know that should be in the running of the estate.
老爷的想法呢
What does his lordship think?
格兰瑟姆伯爵认为亲自打点一切
Lord Grantham thinks his duty is to protect Mary and her son
来保护玛丽和她儿子是他的职责
by managing everything himself.
而且在这件事上他听不进你的话
And he won't listen to you on the subject?
他还把她看做是一个小姑娘
He sees her as a little woman,
不该承受现实残酷的折磨
who shouldn't be troubled by anything so harsh as reality.
就算我同意你的看法
And even were I to agree with you...
我又能帮上什么忙呢
..How could I help?
给她点建议  她会听你的
Give her advice. She'd take it from you.
何出此言
What makes you say that?
因为她明白你所做的都是为她好
Because she knows you only want the best for her.
-我今晚要去酒吧  -什么时候
- I'm going down to the pub tonight. - When?
晚餐之后  我无聊死了  得活动活动
After our supper. I'm bored. I want to stretch my legs.
没得批准你不能去  今天不是你休假
You can't go to the pub without permission. It's not your day off.
我连散个步都不行吗
I can go for a walk, can't I?
-我可不敢用那个  -别这么胆小
- I could never do that. - Don't be so soft.
我就是不敢  老觉得自己会被电死
I couldn't. I'd keep thinking I were going to be electrocuted.
-你该多点信心  -该多点勇气才对
- You should have more faith. - I should have more courage!
来点酒后之勇如何  艾薇
How about some Dutch courage, Ivy?
今晚和我一起去吧
Why not come with me, tonight?
什么  让我去酒吧
What? Me go to a pub?
还不告假  你疯了吧
Without leave? You must be mad.
有什么大不了  你这辈子就没想过冒点险吗
What's the matter? Don't you ever want to take a chance in life?
我们什么时候会回来
When would we be back?
-你不是真想去吧  -我不知道
- You're not thinking of going?! - I don't know.
我从没坏过规矩
I never do anything I'm not supposed to.
-坏什么规矩  -没什么
- What are you not supposed to do? - Nothing.
-那边是怎么回事  -我在为晚餐做慕斯
- What's going on there? - I'm making the mousse for tonight.
我的天  我们最好再预备点汤
Oh, my God. Well, we'd better have some soup put by.
我可信不过那小玩意儿
I'd rather not rely on that contraption.
-需要帮忙吗  -你会帮忙就好了
- Can I help you? - I doubt you would if you could.
你说什么
I'm sorry?
你为什么没把我对鸡蛋的要求转达给帕特莫太太
Why didn't you give my instructions to Mrs Patmore about the eggs?
因为我不想
Because I didn't feel like it.
再说  为什么茜玻小姐的茶点里不能有蛋呢
Besides, why can't Miss Sybbie have an egg to her tea?
我不必事事都向你禀报
I don't have to explain my decisions to you.
你在这里干活
You're a member of staff,
我说的话都得听
and the orders I give are to be obeyed.
你不也在这里干活吗
And aren't you a member of staff?
和你不一样
Not in that way.
我得回楼上干活儿了
Now, I believe I'm needed upstairs.
我能进来吗
May I come in?
卡森
Carson?
进来吧
Of course.
我先走了  小姐
I'll leave you now, m'lady.
有什么事吗
What can I do for you?
我不知道该怎么开口
Well, I'm not sure how to start,
但在我开口之前
but before I do,
您得知道  我是为了您好
you must know that I would only be as bold as this
才会如此大胆
if I felt it was for your benefit.
现在你吓到我了
Now you're frightening me.
夫人
Your ladyship...
-您有空吗  -怎么了  巴罗
- Do you have a moment? - What is it, Barrow?
我担心一件事  夫人  我...
There's something's worrying me, m'lady and I...
-我实在忍不住了  -怎么了  发生什么事了
- But I can't hold it in any more. - Why? What's happened?
是维斯特保姆
It's Nanny West.
她好像对孩子们
I'm afraid it seems she's been leaving the children
不管不顾
to their own devices.
什么  你是说她不管他们
What? You mean she's neglecting them?
如果不是因为牵涉到两个孩子的安危
I wouldn't have spoken up if it weren't for a...
我是不会说出这件事的
..a little girl and a baby boy being put at risk.
-卡森  这是我的错  -小姐
- Carson, this is my fault. - My lady?
恐怕我让你觉得
I'm afraid I may have encouraged you to feel
你有权用这种口气和我说话
you have the right to address me in this way.
老爷做出了决定
His lordship has made a decision
我很难接受他的管家居然会因此指责他
and I find it hard that his butler should criticise him for it.
不  我不是说
No, I never meant...
你好像并不了解
You do not seem to understand
卡劳利先生的死对我造成了何种影响
the effect Mr Crawley's death has had on me.
至于管理庄园  我不知从何下手
As for managing the estate, I wouldn't know where to start.
但是布兰森先生相信您可以帮上大忙  小姐
But Mr Branson believes you could be very helpful, my lady,
他是代理人  应该很清楚
and as the agent, he should know.
他只是担心老爷会回到老路上
He's just nervous that his lordship will retreat to his old ways
放弃马修先生的改革措施
and abandon all Mr Matthew's reforms.
他会这样做吗
And will he?
如果他做了  你会不赞同吗
If he did, wouldn't you approve?
总之  不管你赞同与否
Anyway, whether you approve or not,
你不该觉得自己有权逾越界限
I'm sorry you feel entitled to overstep the mark.
小姐
My lady?
我们是老朋友了
We're old friends,
我也说过了  我相信这次过失我们都有责任
and as I said, I'm sure this lapse is as much my fault as yours.
但是我建议我们不再提起这事
But, I suggest we don't mention it again.
我先走一步  该下去了
Now, if you'll excuse me, it's time to go down.
您这是任凭自己被打败  小姐
You're letting yourself be defeated, my lady.
如果这样说是"过失"  那我很抱歉
I'm sorry if it's a "Lapse" to say so,
但总得有人说
but someone has to.
佃户午餐准备的怎么样了
How is the luncheon for the tenant farmers coming along?
-我觉得很好  -汤姆
- Well, I think. - Tom?
他们都接受了  除了惠勒伍德的巴恩斯
They've all accepted except for Barnes at Wheelers Wood.
他得去参加妹妹的婚礼
He's sworn to his sister's wedding.
我觉得我们可以原谅他
I think we can forgive him.
我总觉得我的安排冲突了
You know, I have a terrible feeling I've double booked.
是这周六  对吗
It's this Saturday, isn't it?
别担心  我们不请太太
Don't worry. We're not having the wives.
伊迪丝可以主持
Edith can preside.
恐怕不行  我要去伦敦
I can't I'm afraid. I'm going up to London.
-那就玛丽吧  -我
- Mary, then. - Me?
如果乔治现在拥有一半庄园
Well, if George is owner of half the estate now,
难道你不该代表他吗
shouldn't you represent him?
-我  -我不想麻烦玛丽
- Well, I... - I don't want to bother Mary.
-他们会想见到你的  -是的  但是
- They'd like to see you. - I'm sure they would but...
毕竟  如果罗伯特有所不测  得由你来管理
After all, you'll have to run it if anything happens to Robert.
直到乔治成年  或者更久
Until George is of age, or longer.
天啊  为什么大家都来唠叨我
For heaven's sake! Why does everyone keep nagging and nagging?
我丈夫死了  你们难道不懂那是什么意思吗
My husband is dead! Can't you understand what that means?
连战争他都挺过来了
After all he suffered in the war,
他居然死于一场愚蠢的车祸
he's killed in a stupid car crash!
马修死了  他还能再活五十年的
Matthew is dead, 50 years before his time!
难道这还不够我心烦的吗
Isn't that enough for me to deal with?
别来烦我
Just leave me alone!
我就怕这样
Exactly what I was afraid of.
她现在身处噩梦之中
She is living a nightmare.
我们必须都后退
We must all step back and
让她自己慢慢恢复过来
allow her to come through it in her own time.
我说得对吧  妈妈
Aren't I right, Mama?
不对  我们现在不能讨论
No. We can't discuss it now.
慕斯美味极了  卡森  是帕特莫太太做的吗
This mousse is delicious, Carson, is it the work of Mrs Patmore?
想必不是她买来的吧
I suppose she hasn't bought it in?
不是  夫人
I don't think so, your ladyship, no.
那你记得告诉她很美味
Then you must be sure to send her our compliments.
怎么了  儿子  觉得不舒服吗
What's the matter, lad? Are you not feeling well?
不是
No, it's not that.
我不知道  爸爸  只是
Oh, I don't know, Dad. It's just...
只是最近我
It's just lately I...
我不知道我未来会怎样  我
I can't seem to see where I'm going, I'm...
你受到了打击  这样并不奇怪
You've had a shock, and no wonder.
你本该服侍马修先生  一直到老去
You should have been working for Mr Matthew until you were old,
也许还能做到庄园的管家
maybe been butler at the Abbey before you were done.
现在一切都没了  你的薪水也随之而去
Now all that's gone, and your wages with it.
他是个好人  爸爸
He were a nice chap, Dad.
不管我们有什么分歧
You know, whatever the difference between us,
他总是彬彬有礼  和蔼可亲
he were always polite, always kind.
很高兴听到你这样说
I'm glad to hear it.
但是这提高了我的标准  你知道吗
But, it's raised my standards, do you see?
老夫人想让我
I mean, who is this old...bat
周五见的这女人是谁啊
her ladyship wants me to meet on Friday?
听我说
Now, listen.
做你这行
In your game,
想服侍最好的主人  就得做最好的仆人
if you want the best, you've got to be the best.
努力争取
And work at it!
去重新找份好工作
Get yourself back into service, in a good post.
很快你就能找到方法去实现你的目标
And you'll soon find your way to where you'd like to be.
我要走了
I'm leaving.
我不想不告而别
I didn't want to run off without saying good night.
您大概觉得我刚才举止很不得体吧
I suppose you think I behaved very badly down there.
亲爱的  你举止是否得体
My dear, I'm not really very interested
我并不在乎
in whether you behaved badly or well.
-不吗  -不
- No? - No.
我不是你的家庭教师  我是你奶奶
I am not your governess. I'm your grandmother.
-哪里不同  -不同在于
- And the difference is? - The difference is...
我爱你
I love you.
我知道
Of course you do.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
玛丽  你很痛苦
Mary, you've gone through a hideous time.
但现在你得为你儿子着想
But now you must remember your son.
他非常需要你
He needs you...very much.
我知道
I know.
老实说  我不觉得我会是个称职的母亲
The truth is, I don't think I'm going to be a very good mother.
为什么呢
Why not?
因为不知怎么了  马修死后
Because somehow, with Matthew's death,
他在我身上看到的温柔
all the softness that he found in me
好像慢慢消失了
seems to have dried up and drained away.
或许那本来就是他的想象
Maybe it was only ever there in his imagination.
亲爱的
Now, my dear...
称职的母亲分很多种
..There's more than one type of good mother.
事实上
The fact is,
你面前有两个选择
you have a straightforward choice before you.
你必须做出决定
You must choose...
是消沉避世  或是积极生活
..Either death...or life.
您认为我该选择生活吗
And you think I should choose life?
查理・格里格将住在卡劳利夫人那儿吗
Charlie Grigg is going to stay with Mrs Crawley?
他被放出来了  卡劳利夫人监管他
The authorities have released him into her charge.
我周五去接他
I'm collecting him on Friday.
为什么她会同意呢
But why has she agreed to this?
因为她很善良  他需要帮助
Because she is a kind woman, and he is a man in need.
我不敢相信
I cannot believe you are
你在这时候还打搅卡劳利夫人
imposing on Mrs Crawley at a time like this,
她经受着丧子之痛
when she is almost broken by grief.
就是因为这样  我才要打搅她
It's BECAUSE of her grief I am imposing.
-我不理解  -不
- I don't understand you. - No.
你不能理解
You wouldn't.
你得原谅玛丽
You must forgive Mary.
我原谅她了
I do forgive her.
她遍体鳞伤  我们得保护好她
She is broken and bruised and it is our job
让她不再受伤害
to wrap her up and keep her safe from the world.
不  罗伯特
No, Robert.
我们要让她重新面对这个世界
It is our job to bring her back to the world.
-我不这样认为  -真的吗
- I'm afraid that is not how I see it. - Really?
那我只能说
Then I can only say that
我可以不介意玛丽做的错误决定
while I will overlook Mary's poor judgement,
但你就不应该了
I find it hard to overlook yours.
晚安
Goodnight.
伊迪丝  伊迪丝  周五一起吃饭吧
Oh, Edith, Edith, come to luncheon on Friday.
-我...  -一定要来
- I... - I mean it.
我需要你的帮助才能成功
I need your help to make things a success.
为什么  我们要做什么
Why? What are we doing?
我们要把莫斯利介绍给沙克尔顿夫人
We are selling Molesley to Lady Shackleton.
是介绍他去做仆人
You mean as a servant?
不  介绍他去洗衣服
No. As a Chinese laundryman
幸好你是一个人  你得帮我
Thank God you're alone. You've got to help me.
你们俩怎么了
What's the matter with you two?
不知道  我跟着他去看看吧
I don't know, but I'd better go with him if I want to find out.
天啊  你怎么了
Oh, my Lord, what have you done?
她在酒吧喝高了
She got a bit tiddly down the pub.
-她不是喝高了  她都醉了  -他一直买酒
- She's not tiddly. She's drunk! - He kept buying them.
-你想做什么  -我没想做什么
- What were you trying to do? - Nothing.
她只是很少喝酒
She's just not used to it.
走吧
Come on.
-怎么回事  -艾薇不舒服
- What on earth?! - Ivy's not very well.
岂止是不舒服啊  快扶她进来
That's the understatement of the year. Bring her inside.
-帕特莫太太睡了吗  -应该睡了  谢天谢地
- Has Mrs Patmore gone to bed? - She must have, thank goodness.
-你想做什么  -我没想做什么
- What were you trying to do? - I wasn't trying to do anything.
最好是这样
As long as you weren't.
来擦脸
Here.
-感觉怎样  -好点了  谢谢
- How are you feeling? - A bit better, thank you.
你差点闯大祸了
You could have done real damage.
-跟我来  -贝茨先生怎么办
- You come along with me now. - What about Mr Bates?
他不会找你吗
Won't he be missing you?
贝茨先生得等着了
Mr Bates must wait his turn.
我真不是存心的  艾薇
Meant no harm, Ivy, honest.
你不会把这事说出去吧
You won't say anything about this, will you?
当然不会
'Course not.
来吧
Come on.
我不是故意的
It wasn't deliberate, you know.
我知道你假装喜欢她来让我难堪
I know you only pretend to like her to tease me.
为什么你不告诉她  那张卡不是你寄的
Why don't you tell her you didn't send that card?
早安  卡劳利夫人  我不知道您来了
Oh good morning, Mrs Crawley. I didn't know you were here.
阿尔弗雷德让我进来的
Alfred let me in.
我来见我孙子
I wanted to see Master George,
不过维斯特保姆觉得现在不合适
but I'm afraid...Nanny West didn't think it a good time.
卡劳利夫人
Oh, er, Mrs Crawley...
我听说您要收留格里格先生
I understand you are offering shelter to Mr Grigg.
对  他今天下午就到
Yes. He's arriving this afternoon.
只是  我不希望您是为了我
Only I should hate to feel you were doing this
才这么做的
out of consideration for me.
格里格先生完全能处理好自己的事情
Mr Grigg is perfectly capable of managing his own affairs.
可他都落魄到救济院了
Not very successfully if he ends up in a workhouse.
我只是不希望您把精力和善心浪费在
I just don't want you to waste your energy and kindness
不值得的人身上
on an unworthy recipient.
起码不是这种时候
Not at such a time.
我懂
I understand.
不过  卡森
But you see, Carson,
我差点要忘记自己还有精力和善心了
I'd almost forgotten I had either energy or kindness in me.
这不是很让人欣慰吗
So that's something, isn't it?
-她为什么要去里彭见她  -不知道
- Why is she seeing her in Ripon? - I don't know.
夫人不等广告结果了吗
Her ladyship won't wait for the advertisement?
要是这位不合格  她会继续等
She will if this one's no good,
但她想赶快办妥
but she wants to get on with it.
你感觉怎么样了  艾薇
How are you, Ivy?
不太好
Not wonderful.
谁都有年轻的时候
I suppose we were all young once.
对  不过你永葆青春
Yes, but you stayed young.
这点跟别人不一样
That's the difference.
不好意思  布雷思韦特小姐
Forgive me, Miss Braithwaite,
我总觉得自己以前见过你
but I have the strangest feeling I've seen you before.
是的  我正准备提这件事
Well, yes. I was just coming to that.
我曾经在唐顿庄园做过工  不过时间很短
You see, I worked at Downton Abbey, but only for a short time.
为什么呢
Why was that?
我当时做的是女仆  夫人
I was a housemaid then, m'lady,
我觉得该做点更有难度的工作
and I was starting to feel it was time to move on.
是这样啊
I see.
我报名上了美发课  我还会做针线活
So, I took a course in hairdressing, and I could always sew.
后来你做了贴身女仆
And you got a job as a lady's maid.
是的  夫人  但只做了几个月
I did, m'lady, but it only lasted for a few months
因为我侍奉的老夫人去世了
because the old lady I was working for died.
真遗憾
I am sorry.
我知道自己的资历不深  夫人
I know I don't sound very experienced, m'lady,
但我很勤快  而且我还练过手了
but I'm a very hard worker and I've practised what I've learned.
要是你之前在唐顿做过工的话
Well, I shall obviously have to talk to Mrs Hughes
我得问一下休斯太太
if you've worked for us before.
我走的时候  她还给我写了封很不错的推荐信呢
She gave me a wonderful reference. When I left.
这点确实很有说服力
That does seem very encouraging.
快答应吧  柯拉堂亲
Please say yes, Cousin Cora.
你真的想做这份工作吗
You definitely want the position?
是的  夫人  我很喜欢唐顿这个地方
Oh, I do, m'lady. I enjoyed Downton ever so much.
我当时只是觉得那份工作没太有挑战性
It was just that the work wasn't sufficiently demanding.
你什么时候能上岗
When would you be able to start?
听您吩咐  夫人
Whenever you want me, your ladyship.
-你能安排好你姨妈的事吗  -我姨妈
- You can make arrangements for your aunt? - My aunt?
你不就是因为要照顾她
I thought that was why you couldn't
才不能去唐顿面试吗
come to Downton for the interview.
抱歉  是这样的
I'm sorry. Of course it was.
我能得到这份工作都有点晕头了
I'm quite dizzy I've got the job.
我能安排好我姨妈的事
Erm, yes, I can make arrangements for my aunt.
您用不着担心
Don't worry about that.
那就这么定了
It's settled, then.
我一个人完全可以为三位夫人侍奉午餐
I'm perfectly capable of serving luncheon to three ladies.
你来做什么
So, why are you here?
我觉得她想把我介绍给沙克尔顿夫人
I've an idea that she wants to introduce me to Lady Shackleton.
这不是你自己的主意吗
Are you sure this isn't your idea?
是不是你让老夫人为你做引荐
I wonder if you haven't pushed her ladyship into it,
这样你就可以在她面前出风头了
so you could just show off in front of her.
当然不是
Certainly not!
我觉得你想抢我的位置
I think it's my job you're after!
-这根本就与沙克尔顿夫人无关  -才不是呢
- Nothing to do with Lady Shackleton. - No!
我凭什么信你
So you say.
我要去宣布开饭了
Well, I'm going to announce luncheon.
我警告你  别打其他主意了
But I'm warning you. That's all.
我儿子告诉我  撤销农产品补贴的决定
My son tells me that this decision to remove the farm subsidies
对全国上下的地产打击非常大
has dealt a terrible blow to landed estates up and down the country.
那个劳合・乔治先生太过分了
That awful Mr Lloyd George.
我也这么觉得
I agree.
我时常怀疑他是不是德国人
You know, I sometimes wonder if he isn't really German,
只是假装成威尔士人而已
just pretending to be Welsh.
见到你真高兴  莫斯利
It's nice to see you here, Molesley.
莫斯利一直都在勤勤恳恳地扶持这个家
Molesley's always been a great supporter of the family.
真好
That's good to hear.
是啊  我和奶奶经常说
Oh, yes, Granny and I are always saying
-莫斯利最可靠了  -没人比得上他
- there's no-one more reliable than Molesley. - No-one.
小心点  莫斯利先生
Careful, Mr Molesley!
你没事吧  莫斯利
Oh? Are you quite well, Molesley?
没事  老夫人
Yes, your ladyship.
你在伦敦做什么  伊迪斯
What are you doing in London, Edith dear?
就是见一些人
Oh you know, seeing people.
你用不着大喊大叫吧  我又没做错什么
There's no need to shout! I wasn't doing anything wrong.
我还以为你要失手掉到地上了
It looked to me as if you were about to drop it.
-我没有  -那就好
- Well, I wasn't. - Very well.
给  上这道菜
Here, take this.
莫斯利  你怎么了
Molesley?
对不起  老夫人
I'm sorry, m'lady.
我不知道这个盘子这么烫
I didn't realise the plate was so hot.
可怜人  他似乎没怎么做过这些呢
Poor man. He seems quite new to this kind of work.
是吗
Does he?
不不  不是这样的  这正是莫斯利的优点
Oh, but that is, no dear no, that is Molesley's strength.
他总是愿意迎接挑战
You see he is always ready for a challenge.
那您允许他做这样的尝试真是太好心了
I think it was very kind of you to allow him to have a go at it.
嗯  我们也是尽力而为嘛
Yes well, we, we try to do our best.
如今有很多人不得不做一些
I do find it very hard these days to see how many men
他们力所不能及的事  真是难为他们了
are forced to take employment for which they are quite unsuited.
希望你能尽快回去做你的本职
I hope you'll soon get back to whatever it is you're trained for.
来吧  格里格先生  休斯太太把你的事都告诉我了
Come in, Mr Grigg. Mrs Hughes has told me all about you.
谢谢您  卡劳利夫人
Thank you, Mrs Crawley.
查理来没来啊
I was er... I was wondering if Charlie might be here.
-查理・卡森  -没有  卡森先生很忙
- Charlie Carson. - No. Mr Carson's very busy.
但我会转告他你安全到达了
But, I'll tell him that you've arrived safely.
但他知道我要来吧
But, he does know I'm coming here?
我们昨天谈过了
We talked of it yesterday.
我给你放了洗澡水
Now, I've run a bath
还在教堂找到了些募捐的干净衣物
and dug out some clean clothes from the missionary barrel.
应该会合身  回头再去弄些更好的衣服来
They should fit you, at least until we can find something better.
这边走  格里格先生
This way, Mr. Grigg.
-您太好了  -哪里的话  这不算什么
- You're very kind. - Nonsense. It's the least I can do.
我去安排他住下
While I'm sorting him out,
你去一趟厨房
I wondered if you'd look in at the kitchen
告诉菲尔德太太他来了
and tell Mrs Field he's arrived
拿托盘把午餐端给他  好吗
and to put his luncheon on a tray.
我觉得他今天该卧床休息
I think he should stay in bed today
然后再做打算
and then we can see where we are.
他说得对  您真是好心
He's right. You're very kind.
不不  我们都得尽力而为嘛
No, no. We must all do what we can.
你好啊
Hello.
你可...真美
You look...very glamorous.
我觉得我该好好打扮一下
I thought I'd make a bit of an effort.
真是太好了
I'm glad you did.
我点了些酒
I've ordered some wine for us.
天呐  真奢侈呢
Heavens, how spoiling.
我很喜欢这里
I love the Criterion.
感觉好疯狂
It feels so wild.
跟一个男人出来私会
To be out with a man,
在伦敦的奢华饭店吃饭喝酒
drinking and dining in a smart London restaurant.
别说十年前  就是五年前  你能想象
Can you imagine being allowed to do anything of the sort
做这样的事吗
five years ago, never mind ten?
战争改变了一切
The war changed everything.
妈妈曾说我们绝不会在公共场所吃饭的
Mama used to say we could never eat anywhere public,
除非是我们下榻的酒店
except an hotel we were staying in.
她可能会带我们去丽兹酒店  但也就那样了
She might cheat and take us to the Ritz, but that was about it.
我好爱你
I do love you so.
是吗
Do you?
那真好
I'm glad.
我们就是为此庆祝吗
Is that what we're celebrating?
对  还有我取得的进展
That, and my progress.
我发现我可以在德国跟莉兹离婚
I've found out I can divorce Lizzie in Germany,
前提是我成为德国公民
if I become a German citizen.
你愿意为我成为德国人
You're willing to become a German citizen, for me?
你真愿意这么做
You'd do that?
如果我能娶你  我愿意成为爱斯基摩人
I'd become an Eskimo if it meant I could marry you.
但是  德国
But...Germany?
我们打了四年的仗
After four years of fighting,
你愿意为我加入欧洲最令人仇视的民族吗
you'd join the most hated race in Europe for me?
我能吻你吗
Can I kiss you?
在这儿吗
What, here?
-当着这么多人的面  -我不在乎
- In front of all these people? - I don't care.
吻我吧
Kiss me. Now.
艾德娜・布雷思韦特要回来了
Edna Braithwaite is coming back?
我本想先跟你商量  但是
I would have talked it over with you first but...
我看到你给她写了那么好的一份推荐信
When I saw that wonderful reference you wrote her.
是  可那是因为
Yes, but that was because...
我给她写了一份好推荐信
I wrote her a good reference
因为我觉得她干活儿勤快利索
because I thought she was a good worker,
但我不觉得她能当好贴身女仆
but I don't see her as a lady's maid.
您不能等到收到广告回复之后
Couldn't you wait for the replies to the advertisement, m'lady,
再做决定吗  夫人
before coming to a decision?
真没想到  休斯太太
I'm surprised at you, Mrs Hughes.
你真要阻止我帮助一个努力勤快的女孩吗
Do you want to prevent my giving a hard-working woman a helping hand?
那张卡的确是吉米寄给艾薇的
You know, it WAS Jimmy sent that card to Ivy.
这你又不确定
You don't know that.
我想没错
I think I do.
可如果是他  那么我那张就是阿尔弗寄的
But, if it were him, then Alfie must have sent mine.
阿尔弗雷德  跟我来
Alfred. Come with me.
-什么事  -你管呢  来就是了
- Why? - Never you mind. Just come along.
莫斯利先生
Mr Molesley?
你要来点什么吗
Can I get you anything?
-来杯茶  -不不  不麻烦你了
- A cup of tea? - No. I don't want to be a bother.
那顿午餐怎么样  伊迪丝小姐告诉我了
How was the famous luncheon? Lady Edith told me all about it.
之前还是之后说的
Was that before or after?
之前
Before.
那就这样吧  别再多说了
Right. Let's just leave it at that, shall we?
休斯太太在找我
Mrs Hughes was looking for me.
我看见她会休息室了  要我去叫她吗
I saw her go into her sitting room. Shall I fetch her?
不必了
No need.
很抱歉我之前没说
I'm sorry not to have mentioned it.
是我给艾薇寄了卡片
I sent the card to Ivy.
但是  吉米说
But...Jimmy said...
他没寄
He didn't send one.
如果他寄了  也没寄给唐顿的人
Or, if he did, it wasn't to anyone at Downton.
晚安  帕特莫太太
Good night, Mrs Patmore.
如果不是他  那是谁寄了卡片给我
If it weren't him, then who did send my card?
我这下睡不着了
I won't sleep now.
老天啊  是我寄的
Oh, for heaven's sake! I sent it.
-你  -对
- You?! - Yes.
我猜到阿尔弗雷德会给艾薇寄一张
I thought Alfred would buy one for Ivy,
如果他寄了  我不希望你什么都没收到
and I didn't want you to have nothing to open if he did.
如果我不该这么做  那很抱歉
I'm sorry if I did wrong.
不  别这么说
No, don't be sorry.
我虽然没有人暗恋  但至少有个好朋友
I may not have a follower, but at least I've got a friend.
晚安  帕特莫太太
Goodnight, Mrs Patmore.
我真不知道该怎么说
I didn't know what else to say.
我的确给她写了份好推荐信
I had written her a good reference.
但那是因为我求您
Only because I asked you to.
那我该告诉夫人吗  布兰森先生
And was I to tell her that, Mr Branson,
还有您提出要求的原因
and why you asked me?
我去告诉她吧
It's up to me to tell her.
是我搅起了这场麻烦
I'm the one who got us into this fix.
不
No.
夫人失去了一个女儿和一个女婿
Her ladyship has lost a daughter and a son-in-law.
我不能让她觉得茜玻小姐的丈夫做了有失体面的事
I cannot now let her think that Lady Sybil's husband was unworthy.
这对她会难以承受
It's too much.
那我们怎么做
Then what are we to do?
-不能留她在这儿  -不行也得行
- We can't have her here. - We must.
我们让她回来
We'll let her come back
并且保证她不会逾矩
and we'll make sure that she behaves herself.
如果她不守规矩呢
And if she doesn't?
我们得盯紧了她
We must keep a firm eye on her,
希望我们可以指望你
and I hope we may rely on you
确保艾德娜不会做什么出格的事
to see that Edna doesn't step out of line.
当然
Of course.
毕竟  她似乎的确接受了专业的训练
After all, she does appear to have acquired some proper training.
这应该不假
I don't think that's a lie.
或许她变得现实了
Maybe she's moved into the real world.
我觉得就是颗定时炸弹
Well, it all sounds like a ticking bomb to me.
好了  我的好宝贝
There, there, my precious boy,
别让那司机的女儿再打扰你了
and don't let that chauffeur's daughter disturb you any more.
给我睡觉
Go back to sleep,
你个小杂种
you wicked little cross-breed.
夫人  我没看见您
Your ladyship... I didn't see you there.
显然如此
Obviously not.
我就是...
I was just er...
我就是跟茜玻小姐闹着玩呢
I was just having a game with Miss Sybbie.
我要你今晚收拾东西  明天一早就走
I want you to pack tonight and leave first thing in the morning.
但是  夫人
But, your ladyship...
请把乔治少爷放回摇篮里
Please put Master George back into his crib.
你不许再碰两个孩子了
You are not to touch the children again.
我以为是维斯特保姆按的铃呢
Oh. I thought it was Nanny West ringing.
不  休斯太太  维斯特保姆明早就会走了
No, Mrs Hughes, Nanny West is leaving in the morning.
请你为她找张床  让她今晚过夜
Can you find her a bed for the night
找一个女仆来陪孩子睡
and ask one of the maids to sleep with the children?
但是  夫人  我就是说笑呢
But, your ladyship, I was only joking.
我不想再说了
I prefer not to discuss it,
除了告诉你
except to say that
你这样的观念在一个文明的家里待不下去
your values have no place in a civilised home!
好了  休斯太太
Now, Mrs Hughes...
维斯特保姆收拾东西的时候我就等在这儿
I'll wait here while Nanny West packs.
你去找个女仆来  再收拾一间房
You will fetch a maid and prepare a room.
要记住  不能让维斯特小姐跟孩子独处
You understand, Miss West is not to be left alone with the children.
一分钟也不行
Not for one minute.
不知道伊迪丝怎么样了
I wonder how Edith's getting on.
她去伦敦去得很频啊
She has quite a London life.
-她在跟她的编辑约会  -是认真的吗
- She's seeing that publisher. - Is it serious?
他长得不差  而且还喘气
Well, he's not bad looking and he's still alive,
这样他与我们同龄的男士相比就有两项优势了
which puts him two points ahead of most men of our generation.
可是她能找个比他更好的
Which doesn't alter the fact she could do a great deal better.
-你了解他吗  -不怎么了解
- Do you know anything about him? - Not really.
我们在唐依阁的时候  他跟马修谈过
He talked to Matthew a bit when we were at Duneagle...
回房去吧
Go to bed.
你看起来很疲惫
You look done in.
明天的佃户午餐  您需要我去吗
Do you want me at the tenants' luncheon tomorrow?
你不必出席
No, there's no reason for you to be.
我知道您想保护我
I know you're trying to shield me...
让我用自己的方式来打理吧
Let me manage things in my own way.
听我的  这样最好
Please. It'll be for the best.
我也有想法的  马修和我以前常常谈...
I have ideas, you know. Matthew and I used to talk...
亲爱的  我知道我是对的
My dear, I know I'm right in this.
去睡吧
Now, go to bed.
小姐
My lady?
抱歉这么晚来打搅你
I'm sorry to bother you so late,
但我想你知道我为何事而来
but I think you know why I've come.
-我是来道歉的  -您不必道歉
- To apologise. - You have nothing to apologise for.
是我唐突了  说了不该说的话
I pushed into your room and I spoke impertinently.
我想你知道奶奶赞同你的观点
I suppose you know my grandmother agrees with you.
这我并不奇怪
That doesn't surprise me.
这么说  您是决定
So, does this mean you've decided
回到生活中来了吗
to return to the land of the living?
如果是这样  我很高兴
Because, if so, I'm glad.
我只是
It means that I
意识到我已经颓废消沉太久了
know that I've spent too long in the land of the dead.
我们都很喜欢卡劳利先生  小姐
We were very fond of Mr Crawley, you know, my lady.
我们所有人
All of us.
我
I...
哭吧  小姐
You cry, m'lady.
好好哭一场
You have a good cry.
现在该把眼泪都流出来
That's what's needed now.
等您准备好了
And when you're ready...
就可以做您该做的了
..You can get to work.
因为您很坚强
Because you are strong enough.
您能承受这份考验
You're strong enough for the task.
是吗  卡森
But am I, Carson?
问题就在这儿  爸爸似乎不这么想
That's the point. Papa doesn't seem to think so.
难道您不该为了卡劳利先生  保护他的遗志吗
Don't you owe it to Mr Crawley, to protect his work?
努力维护他所做出的变革
To fight for the changes he made?
让唐顿走上正确的道路
To steer Downton in the right direction?
我知道我怀疑自己的时候
I know I can always count on you
你肯定会为我鼓劲
for a draught of self-confidence whenever I start to doubt.
我永远都在这儿
And you will always find one here.
晚安  卡森
Good night, Carson.
晚安  小姐
Good night, m'lady.
我的天
Oh my gosh.
这是怎么了
Ohh... What in God's name...?
肯定是叉子放得不是地方
I must have put those ruddy prongs in wrong.
你肯定有什么没做对
You did something wrong.
今天可真够精彩的
What a day this has turned out to be.
怎么了
Why?
维斯特保姆被解雇了
Nanny West has been sacked.
明天有得说了
So, that's fun for tomorrow.
如果有人看见了这个我也得被解雇了
Well, I'll get the sack if anyone sees this!
让黛茜和艾薇早上来收拾吧
Let Daisy and Ivy clean it up in the morning.
哪能让黛茜知道我不会使用这个
But Daisy mustn't find out I don't know how to work it.
为什么
Why ever not?
那样她就是未来
Because it makes her part of the future
而我就被留在过去了  你还不明白吗
and leaves me stuck in the past, don't you see?
给我件围裙  我们一起收拾
Oh... Fetch me an apron. We'll do it together.
-真的吗  -有何不可
- Would you, really? - Why not?
睡觉有什么好
Who needs sleep?
谢谢
Thank you.
-我一直不是很喜欢她  -维斯特保姆吗
- I was never sure I liked her. - Nanny West?
虽然这事轮不到我说
It's not for me to have an opinion,
但我还是要说
but I will say this...
你昨晚去哪了
Where did you get to last night?
我进来之前我就睡着了
I was fast asleep before you came in
我走的时候你还在睡
and you were sleeping when I left.
我的确睡得很晚
I'm afraid it was very late.
但是你来得正好  我想告诉你
But I'm glad you're here now because I want you to know
我们真是要好好感谢巴罗
that we owe a great debt to Barrow, here.
我发现维斯特小姐非常不适合做保姆
It turns out Miss West is quite unsuited to the role of Nanny.
-她今天就走人  -什么  又是这样
- She is leaving today. - What? Not another one.
相信我  回头再说  我得走了  要迟了
Trust me. We'll talk about it later. I must run or I'll be late.
巴罗  我是真心的  谢谢你
Barrow, I meant what I said. Thank you.
我很高兴  夫人
I'm glad, your ladyship.
我就是觉得她不是那么称职
I just had a hunch that she wasn't quite all Sir Garnet.
这我不介意  你先测试一下就好
I've no problem, as long as you test them first.
真抱歉没能去迎接大家
I'm so sorry to miss your arrival.
没事  小姐  我们还没开席呢
That's all right, m'lady. We've not begun to eat.
-来坐这儿吧  -我就坐这儿就好
- Come and sit here. - I'll manage very well at the end.
卡森去给我搬个椅子来吧
Carson can find me a chair.
坐这儿吧  我去那边坐
No. Sit here. I'll go to the end.
这才是你该坐的地方
This is your place.
你真的有这个时间吗
Are you sure you have time for this?
当然
Quite sure.
我一直很期待呢
I've been looking forward to it.
泰勒先生
Now, Mr Taylor.
你说要放弃牧羊是怎么回事
What's all this I hear about your giving up sheep?
小姐  事情可不是那么简单
Well, m'lady, it's not quite as simple as that.
说实话  我宁可放牧
If truth be told, I'd rather be farming livestock...
为什么
And why is that?
下集预告
-我找到一封马修的信  -放在哪的
- There's a letter from Matthew. - Where was it?
放在办公室一本书里
Hidden in a book in the office.
你是想逃避真相吗
Are you trying to hide from the truth?
你更希望能独自经营唐顿
That you would prefer to be in sole charge of the estate.
布雷思韦特和安娜之间有些矛盾
There's bad feeling between Braithwaite and Anna.
-老爷  -安娜待她不太友善
- M'lord? - Anna has been a little unkind.
-什么那么好笑  -没什么  贝茨先生
- What's so funny? - Nothing, Mr Bates.
我想让汤姆来指导你
I want "Tom" to be your instructor.
我们做这些要瞒着爸爸吗
Are we to do all this without telling Papa?
待人接物  有些事不能说得太明白了
There can be too much truth in any relationship.
罗斯小姐问我能不能陪她去俱乐部
Lady Rose asked me if I'd chaperone her to a The Dansant.
你一定别让她惹麻烦
Make sure you keep her out of trouble.
你想被逮捕吗
Do you want to be arrested?
翻译   真月镜威
翻译   Leona
翻译   猫中之王
翻译   爵士年代蓬蓬裙
翻译   卫老哥
翻译   鱼小姐啦
翻译   冰蓝
翻译   小马子咧
翻译   你是不是饿得慌
翻译   草草
时间轴   子衿
时间轴   今
后期   瓜瓜
校对   草草
总监   草草
唐顿庄园
YYeTs人人影视英剧社倾情奉献
第四季  第一集